Well, we thought, starting with the image of Black, like the Spinal Tap album.
Alright, here we go.
So, okay, for those of you film buffs, I wanted to use Back in Black.
Marvel has never paid the, you know, six-figure price for it, and I think we ended up, to save money, not actually having
credits run over the song. Do we want this fucking light on the whole time?
My kids are here.
So you see there's no music playing.
See? Now once the credits go off, watch what happens.
There you go.
We saved $150,000.
Oh, we gotta crank this up - you're killing me.
We'll go a little bit more - we're loud. So this is actually in Lone Pine, California.
And that's not an Arab, but it is a Mexican with a goat.
Just let this play, it's too good.
We re-cut this scene about 50,000 times.
There he is.
I'm actually chewing Nicorette gum right there.
Much of this is improvised.
There are other versions of this where he's dancing to Tom Jones singing Prince's Kiss.
We went a different way.
Robert and I were constantly fighting about whether or not Tony Stark would wear a tie.
And so you'll see that sometimes the button's open, sometimes the tie's up, sometimes the tie's down.
Jon, no offense, I can't hear myself in this scene. You gotta crank it up, this is too good.
So we wanted to here create a sense that we weren't really taking the setting of the war seriously.
He's joking, you're having a good time...
Then in the back of this frame, it was very hard to get the explosion to
go off without tipping it. So if you look, hopefully you're not expecting it.
We wanted to have a tonal shift in the film.
Jon actually pushed the button on that detonation.
And I was riding in that Humvee behind them with a helmet on, and they pulled me aside, and he says, I have to tell you...
Can you turn it down a little bit? He says, I have to tell you, you can really get hurt.
I said, I don't understand, you told me it was safe in all the meetings.
He says, yeah, it is safe. We did everything we could.
But you can get very hurt if something goes wrong.
I just have to tell you that. And I said, so like, do you tell me not to do it?
He says, no, do it. I just have to tell you - You can really get hurt. The phone was my idea. Yes, it was.
Oh, this was a fun day.
Yeah, we threw the... We kept throwing stuff in his face. We kept blowing an air mortar in his face.
It never happened quite right.
This is actually a visual effect. Not totally happy with the way that it turned out.
We did 12 fittings for this vest.
Yeah.
For me to lie on my back wearing it. There it is.
The vest.
So, here he is waking up. So that was sort of the vision. You start off with him joking around, having
a cocktail, a suit, looking like a fish out of water.
And then, boom, you're at a beheading video.
And that was going to tell you.
That somewhere between those two... Between those two things, that's our story.
Is Matty Libatique here tonight, Jon? Is Matty here? I saw Matty today - I told him to stop by.
I haven't seen him. Fantastic Director of Photography.
Real pictures of Robert.
I like that. Bill Gates.
So many meetings about every frame of this thing. Because there's so much backstory in here.
Most of this is based on what's in the comic books.
I was just in Japan promoting the movie.
And somebody told me that was, what we just saw was the best part of the movie.
And I didn't even put it together -
it was Kyle Cooper.
Very talented guy. I like that. Nice touch.
Rolling Stones thing.
Looks like the Republican National Convention.
We sort of wanted an upbeat feel.
This was actually not shot in Caesars Palace. But we had to show the logo from Caesars Palace.
Otherwise they were going to hit us with a big bill for shooting in Caesars Palace.
This was in The Biltmore, downtown [L.A.] and then we added the podium.
So I saved another $100,000.
Okay, this theme song that we recorded is the theme song from the 60's Iron Man cartoon.
Not many people caught that.
And we used it again in the casino in another version.
So this is... I hate to ruin it for you guys. This guy ends up being the bad guy,
Jeff Bridges.
And this is where we sort of have to set up a little bit that he's jealous.
Also later in the film as well.
To somehow create a paper cutout of a motive to justify the big fight at the end.
It took him about 8 hours to shave his head, a 16th of an inch at a time.
And I sat with him in the makeup trailer
As he got comfortable with it.
Here's me. Jon Favreau, ladies and gentlemen.
Everybody thought this was Hilary Swank.
And there was internet rumors. But it actually isn't Hilary Swank.
This was pretty much improvised. This was our last day of filming in Vegas.
With real casino goers gathered around. Remember that?
And Vince Vaughn was actually there off camera watching, cheering us on.
I was very adamant that we use real chocolate chips. The $5,000 chips.
So they had to have it.
A few million dollars on the table there.
The prop guy wanted to use fake ones. I said, no, I can't. Jon Favreau can't do a Vegas movie with fake chips.
When we were done shooting, we shot a suicide split from midnight to noon.
I remember that Vince was there.
And Jon took off his tux. He just had his t-shirt on. And it literally looked like a snapshot from
Swingers at one point.
I, of course, wasn't in Swingers...
This was the scene that he did in his screen test. And he killed it. It was even better than this.
He never hit that level.
And the first scene in the movie was a screen test scene too. Which he actually, by the time we were
shooting the first scene, he was just giving me good lines over a walkie-talkie. I think that's on the DVD.
I think the screen test scenes are on the DVD.
I thought everything was.
This is how Tony Stark handles liberal journalists... coming up.
A little shot there.
That's right, bitch.
So there you go. We have the James Bond fantasy. How many different ways did we shoot this?
There's one where she slaps him.
Remember she slapped you once? Do I remember!?
She slapped me! So that's the scene that I had to re-cut 15 times.
Not because the rating was bad, but because the language of some sexual or sensual content
was unacceptable to Paramount and Marvel. Not the rating, but the language.
That ILM did. Isn't that great? I mean, it's fantastic.
I hate CGI.
But I was on their ass, and I'm happy with that. I think they really nailed it.
We added some movement in the water. People go crazy looking for this house at at Point Dume.
I love it. I did seem to me they should have advertised it, "with some ceiling damage."
We put an ad with that photo in the LA Times real estate section. And if you went to the website, it
took you to the Iron Man thing.
Here's Gwyneth on a broken leg.
Now this is my real hot rod, and Robert decided instead of gapping the spark plugs, that he wanted to rip the engine block
apart.
There it is. Look at him.
Jay Leno said, it's clear that that guy does not know what he's doing.
I said, I know, it's my car.
And Paul Bettany's voice . He did a favor for me.
I met him on Wimbledon. Jarvis, the computer, is Paul Bettany's voice.
I love this scene.
So that little bit of dialogue... about her correcting him about the springs period -
was actually Gwyneth correcting me when she read the script. She says, no, it's actually not the spring
period. It's springs period.
I said, this is too good. I've gotta put this in.
I love it when somebody's trying not to be condescending but can't help it.
And I love Gwyneth.
She's a wonderful influence on the set. Great person. I've known her for many years.
But you can definitely tell that she has that culture. There is some chemistry going on right there.
Robert made us add this last little moment here.
Because if they were just looking at one another, it would have been too much. He had to walk away.
I handed her my espresso cup.
She's my assistant.
Here's the R8.
Okay, so see this R8?
We smashed up two of them.
For the ending.
And I cut it out of the movie.
And the Audi people said, wait a second.
We gave you a quarter million dollars worth of cars to...
bounced the waiting list... So you could do what you cut out of the movie and say it didn't work.
I love the tail on this [plane] though.
Very happy with that CGI.
You guys see how little Happy Hogan says?
I thought I had more to do, but I cut myself out.
Here's a little improvised bit. Here are two cameras.
We shot all these scenes in six hours.
That's what I'm talking about.
So, Ghostface Killer, who is known as Iron Man in the rap community, wanted to be a part of this.
We filmed the scene, cut it out, but I included him. And this is actually a song he made
for Iron Man.
And we made our own little video with him in the background for...
Jon suggested they put in that dance pole.
Yeah.
Once again, back in Lone Pine.
Everything you've seen so far except for Vegas is in California.
Very adamant about shooting here.
So, this next bit here...
I'm very proud of it.
We wrote it five minutes before we shot it.
It's true.
The reason I'm wearing sunglasses is because Jon said, "cut, I see your eyes reading the cue cards."
We were scribbling on pieces of foam core.
I love it. And by the way, at Comic-Con...
We don't play that part in Japan.
You know, for China, we had to cut everything out. We had to cut so much out, they
don't even ask you.
They're like, you can't mention Genghis Khan. Genghis Khan? Really?
That's the only country we had to change it. The reason this effect is good is because
I rode them like a jockey.
That's good.
I think we could have done better on that one.
I like that. There's a prop man under that pushing it up.
Russell Bobbitt. That's true.
Marvel got very mad he didn't have his shirt on.
But then they gave us the great line, "Why aren't you wearing those pajamas I bought you?" It makes no sense.
It was really important to us.
Another improvised line.
Peter [Billingsley] said, that won't make sense.
Nobody will understand what a Funvee and a Humdrumvee is. He said, okay, we're going to shoot it.
This is a little magic, you see here - Dan Lebental magic. The cinematographer and editor.
So now we're back into real time.
This was our first shot. Correct.
We had the entire cave, which was built on a stage out of mostly styrofoam, believe it or not.
Isn't that nice there?
Thank you.
Another one of my bright ideas.
And we refrigerated the whole set just to get that breath.
Just to get that breath.
It gives it a nice little thing. We back off a bit a few scenes in.
I thought it was always a good idea to make sure that half your cast and crew have the flu before you go on to
the next bit of shooting.
We shot pretty much in continuity, starting from here.
It's a culmination of about 800 hours of meetings looking at drawings of what that thing should look like.
Robert was our technical advisor for how you
handle yourself in small, confined quarters.
Not a joke. He'd come in and say that's how you cook your thing and you need
a sock to make it.
It's good to know that.
Too soon?
Is it too soon?
Too soon.
It's sad.
He was from Crash, by the way - Shaun Taub. Shaun Taub - love him. The most Hollywood guy on the set.
So this guy here, Sayed, came in auditioning for the other role.
There was only one role for the bad guy.
I loved him so much.
He's actually friends with my wife's—
my wife works with somebody who's a nurse
who's his wife.
And you know those stories like,
"Can you just meet with the guy?
I work with his wife, here's a headshot." Yeah, bring him on.
He blew me away. He's like an Egyptian theatre actor,
and he was just a great dude.
And I was like, we gotta figure out how to get him in the movie.
And so we divided the bad guy up into two roles, and one of them is him.
And we actually shot a lot more stuff,
where they became friends, remember, and he actually got bumped off by the other guy, but it didn't...
we had to cut the movie
down from three hours, unfortunately, and that part never made it in.
So we're going to show the movie, and I said, don't we get a scene where he's like
being dunked underwater or something, waterboarded or something like that. And the editor said, can I do it to you?
That's part of the reshoots there, the waterboarding.
We really tried to walk a political line here, where we didn't really- we presented things pretty even-handedly, we didn't want to really
vilify anyone, or present one side politically as wrong or right, but I thought the sense that he was a guy who was oblivious
to the effect that he had had in his life's work, takes sort of A Christmas Carol type approach to the storyline, not that he
becomes a pacifist per se, but he feels
a sense of responsibility in his life.
So this, the actual dialogue in this scene is him going, Carter, Reagan, Bush, Clinton, Bush, and that's all you hear, and then the
other guy says, he says they're all gifts.
That was very sensitive, it didn't quite sit well in the movie, but the idea that weapons have been pouring into this part of the
world for decades of administrations of both parties, and that the nuances over here for what political leanings we have...
That's a nice touch
that you asked the guy to finger his ring. Yeah, the ring, the Ten Rings of the underground.
That was my call, bad call on the hat, sorry folks.
Charles Dickens... Cabin Boy...
So, for you Joseph Campbell fans, there's the refusal of the call [Hero's Journey], and here it is.
We apologize for this hat as well.
That was a great...
This hat, this horrible optional hat, like we don't show up for one day and he puts on a Castro hat, I'm like-
he has such nice hair.
Let's have a little fun with it. Yeah, I'm Robert.
If we told you all this early enough, you'd be amazed that a good movie ever got done. It's true.
So we make a big deal here that they speak all languages, and it's not one particular group, and we're sort of building towards
the Mandarin being the super villain, a movie or two down the road, and that this is only one, this is only one cell
of this larger collective of bad guys.
Pretty convincing, huh? It looks like he knows what he's doing.
I have a spell on the props department, I'll tell you.
Palladium, this was a very big deal to Robert, that that metal be palladium.
You want to hand out the pamphlet with the buffalo now?
He's playing it.
It's a sacred metal.
If you like this part of the movie, we got another hour and a half of it for you.
Just this stuff.
Robert was pretty good at it.
At the end of the day, you've got to cut these movies down as quick as you can.
They all come in at three hours, and you've got to cut it down to an hour and a half, basically.
And I would fight like hell to keep all the little stammers and back and forth and all the scenes with him and Gwyneth,
all the dialogue scenes, which in superhero movies are usually the first ones to get trimmed down to the bone.
But to me, that's where the charm of this movie is.
It's the only part of this movie I really felt confident about, because some of this stuff is real new to me.
And so I fought like a pinball to keep all that stuff in.
You're welcome. Thanks.
Great lighting by Matty, Matty Libatique.
Darren Aronofsky stuff.
Joel Schumacher, Spike Lee.
With his [Matty's] patented flickering ballasts.
In every movie he's done. I said "Aren't you gonna put it in my movie?" It's like Vin Diesel acting in a movie
and not showing his guns. You're not going to give me the flickering fluorescent light?
He even did it in Josie and the Pussycats.
This is a very cool little piece of art direction here.
How many arguments back and forth? Do we show it? If we show it, does it ruin it?
I feel like it doesn't ruin it. I'm glad we got that cutaway.
Passage of time.
You have no idea what these arguments go on behind the scenes. How are they going to know?
Show people warming their hands in a fire. How do they know it's winter?
That's a visual effect, those dice. Because he says, "shesh besh," which means a five and a six
in backgammon in Arab, for a good roll. It wasn't that.
I said, for my movie, it has to be shesh besh if they say "shesh besh."
And that's a visual effect. We changed the number of the dice. Thank you.
Doesn't he look good in this scene, by the way? Robert looks sexy as hell.
Oh, that's Shaun Taub. I'm sorry.
I like how you're looking at it. The hair, the whole thing.
Stolen point of view shot from something else.
How did they not know? I'm going to check.
This is a badass shot. All the Stan Winston stuff. The last movie Stan Winston did.
Great, great, great guy.
He was very... He hadn't had a hit movie in a long time.
It was really nice for him to... He was really, really touched by his experience. And we were as well.
Big fan, big geek.
Big fanboy. You get to sit with him and go through his workshops.
It was a real treat.
Okay, see?
Now it's still winter. Now there's no snow. It's a cold, Indian summer.
That's a [comic book] panel from Adi Granov. You know, him with the goggles on.
This is Faran [Tahir]. He's a great, great guy. All these guys are just the best guys
in the world to hang out with.
They're working their asses off now with like 24 going through three of them a month.
Work like hell. And I'm like, I get it, I get it, yeah.
It's good and it's bad. I get a lot of work, but it takes me six hours to fly to work.
It's true. My friend Ahmed Ahmed is up there. He's a comedian.
I met him through events years ago. This poor guy, he gets thrown in jail-
He said he'll literally, if he's going to fly someplace with me, he says, okay, I'm going to show up six hours ahead of
time. And we'll be on the same flight. And he brings his comedy CDs.
He gives them out. They don't know what to make of him. It's a tough time to have a Muslim
last name if you like to travel via air.
This is what the Chinese government made us cut out. Genghis Khan.
It's a sore subject.
It was a thousand years ago, really?
Let's not open that can of worms.
All right, I'll cut it out. Movie won't make any sense...
Robert really sells this scene. What the hell is going on?
So now this guy is like the super good guy in the new Star Trek movie.
He's like the starship commander, Faran. He worked with J.J.
J.J. Abrams was on the phone with us in the last scene of the movie in my trailer.
I'm like, give me some lines. "What's happening?" "I'm not sure."
This is a very Spielbergian moment here.
The hot coal and everything reminded me of one of the Indiana Jones movie.
Yes, that's right. A different reference there.
Yeah, the Nazi with the poker. We were sort of ripping that off. We ripped off a lot of Lucas in
this movie.
If you notice the wipes to the desert, we used the Star Wars wipes.
Now watch this. A lot of working out led to this moment right here.
Look at that.
So in the comic books, you never really have to wonder how he knows a thing or puts it on.
It doesn't make much sense. Very hard to portray it in a way that feels real.
But we made him a very technically able fellow and I think this little set of props that were developed helped make it at
least plausible so you can enjoy yourselves for the next action sequence.
We really wanted to make it worn.
See, we figured there's only about 400 Hungarians in the world.
Who would be offended if we make a
terrorist Hungarian?
Supposedly what he says in Hungarian, a Hungarian told me isn't Hungarian.
There's a little improvised line here, very poignantly.
He says did it work?
That's what I do.
So it's impossible to create tension in this moment.
More intense. More intense. Go again.
But really when you cut it together you need intensity and it's the hardest thing in the world to fake, and ask someone to fake.
And you need to use music and effects and camera moves.
I'm not good at that yet.
It worked.
Thank you. That's what I was looking for. Thank you.
Why don't you run down the hall and just scream That kind of thing. I just saw that on playback.
Ridiculous.
A little Han Solo.
Do we shoot him? Do we not shoot him? Do we hear him being shot?
This way, that way.
And it's all lost in a reel change anyway. There it is. A reel change.
You never actually watch those two scenes back to back ever in the process. That's a reel change.
So when you're in your sound mix or your DI, you never see how it flows.
And you don't know until you're at the premiere that it worked. Essentially.
They don't teach you that.
So you gotta go back to the Avid [Media Composer] and watch it.
Tom Morello, ladies and gentlemen [famous rock guitarist].
He was so proud to be dressed up as an insurgent.
He had a smile on his face the whole time.
He's a big Iron Man fan and he played guitar for us for this next sequence.
That was my little bit of motion capture when I came behind.
Simple 8mm camera there.
I like this. Just brutal.
And mostly practical suit here, by the way. It's called the Stan Winston suit.
Because we shot in low light most of the stuff is actually the real suit.
And that allowed us to get the footage ready in time for Comic-Con because we weren't relying on CG.
I love this effect right here.
That's what you don't see. Good thing they emptied their clips for no reason.
Full-length humor here.
There we go.
That's CG.
How many rocks should fall on him? Enough that you know he's dead, but not enough that if he's not dead you don't
think it's weird. Well how many rocks is that? Nobody's studying this shit in film school.
Look at that, American flag on the rice bag.
Am I a filmmaker or what?
Get over there. Figure it out. That's one to grow on.
I'm not going to joke, Jon, until this scene is over where we have five pages of goodbye.
So this thing was supposed to be with his helmet closed. We only shot with his helmet open once
in case we wanted to track in under the thing for safety and of course that's the one we used because he did such
a darn good job. You don't have a thoroughbred hauling an ice truck.
For Downey Jr. you've got to get his puss... Hold on, this is my coming out part.
We put a lot of camera shake on this because I never really love the way this one came out.
Real suit.
Real Suit
And real suit.
Real flames here by the way. They really shot fire.
Big flames.
Fake Iron Man.
Real Iron Man. Real Iron Man, fake legs. Palm shot.
Palm shot. Fake flames. Fake Iron Man.
Pretty good.
That's the first time this particular vendor did a movie. A place called The Embassy out in Canada.
About six people working there. Great job on that suit there.
They'd only done commercials before.
Really good motion capture. CG.
That's real, that's fake.
There we go.
There was a 60 mile an hour wind storm and it stopped for 90 seconds, and we got this shot. That's true.
That's quite a guy- we buried him in there.
What would you say? You don't want to be too light because people just died but you're glad you're alive.
You say something middle of the road.
"Not bad."
It's also a long time. Real dunes. That's all real.
No digital stuff in that shot. Can you see that? That thing, well there would be a flame
bar under the camera to get that little heat wave but there's there are real winds kicking up here.
So these are real helicopters about to fly over his head that they really sent in.
They really have them keep going around and around.
The highway was closed and Terrence Howard actually flew in on one of those helicopters.
They told him that they all wear white gloves and I think they were messing with him.
Because he looks like a mime.
So they give you three helicopters but then you wear the gloves. So it was pretty much a wash I think.
Edwards Air Force Base once again.
Matty wanted to wet down the runway to help it out. It just looks like a fuel spill now.
So, all dried up.
Here we go.
A little bit of good acting coming up over here.
Get that thing out of here. I like that.
There's my line. My one line in the movie. Thank you.
That's what these movies never have. Just people talking and talking over all that stuff.
And again, as Jon said, I was a technical consultant for what you want when you get out of captivity.
That's a cheeseburger. I don't know what we can do for a burger
that won't seem too on-the-nose for a Burger King burger. Then I just proceed to eat them into
the next couple of scenes. I even stuck a logo in it. There you go.
It's good for like 15 million in free advertising.
Burger King actually made some really good kids toys for the movie.
Clark Gregg, the director of Choke [2008], being featured here [Aero Theater] in an upcoming week.
And one of our neighbors. I met Clark. He used to live right on 14th Street.
Great actor and now a great director as well. And a great writer.
Everybody in this movie really- very few people had been in a movie like this before.
Gwyneth hadn't, Robert hadn't, I hadn't been involved with one, directing
-wise, he hadn't. And we were really just getting a kick out of the fact that we were making
this kind of movie. Even he. Here he is.
Robert walked in as we lit and rehearsed.
Standing, and said I think It'd be good if I sat down and got everybody else to sit down. Sure.
And I looked at him like I was crazy.
Why are you doing that? Doesn't make any sense. I said, he's just testing me.
He has to trust me. I'm his director. Let's just try it once.
And we did and it worked, so we did it. Then we re-lit the whole scene and it made our day.
So this is a scene that you literally had scrawled out on a napkin from the night before.
This was not in the script this way.
And I think Robert really took it to heart that you can't ok, the press conference
scene where you give out exposition we've seen it a million times before.
Robert's biggest sort of pet peeve was not to
have a scene that seemed mundane, or like you've seen it a thousand times before.
And so he really took it upon himself
to rework this whole scene.
I called Shane Black and asked him...
There's a lot of people I mean, you think that Hollywood's competitive or there's a lot
of backstabbing or people compete. It's kind of not true. Shane Black helped us with some scenes.
J.J. Abrams helped us with some stuff. I helped them. He's helped them.
You know, it's so hard to make these movies that most people if they get a phone call and you're like, I need help,
people will drop whatever they're doing. There you are on screen again, by the way.
Briefly on screen. Well, I was briefly on screen.
That damn thing changed colors like 30 times over the course of production.
Let's figure out what it should look like.
What noise it should make.
I love how conversational these guys are in all the scenes. Not just them, but him and Gwyneth.
Rhodey.
We really tried to hold it to the standard of if it were just like an independent comedy or something.
All these scenes were two cameras. One on Robert, one on Jeff. One on Robert, one on Gwyneth.
One on Robert, one on Terrence.
Because we would change it. We'd mix it up all the time. I always wanted to make sure I could
use anything good that came.
Sometimes composition and lighting was sacrificed. There's not a lot of intricate camera moves in this film.
I prefer to capture something real happening.
So Jeff loved to have a script a good three months before he did the scene.
He would write more notes than I would
have as a director on the opposite page.
Robert would come in and bounce the script off the wall of the trailer every day.
This was a good call.
Nobody thought to put this guy in a movie.
Let's give it a shot.
I like the tone of it.
Her leg was broken in this scene too. She broke her leg over the course of the film.
Not on the film. We found out that she needed surgery. Being the trooper that she was, she...
This is the heart of the movie. This was Jon's idea.
I was sitting in a chair with a prosthesis and fake legs for 12 hours. At the end of the day, that's probably
my favorite scene. Let's just let it play.
You get it? Operation the little, uh... There we go.
Okay.
That was improvised.
What I like about how she does comedy is she's not- she doesn't do comedy,
so she just plays it dead real.
It's cool, the way- I like how people play comedy.
So when they're building all these props and things, they're like, so how deep do you want the thing?
I figure realistically it's going to be about 2 inches. We're like, no, she should be able to
get her whole wrist in there. But that's not real. I said, let me just do it.
If they're laughing, they won't mind.
There's someone standing two feet away from us the whole time with a huge bag of sludge.
They're like, "can I just reset the inorganic plasmic discharge?
And this is what sells the whole thing,
right? So there was a big rubber body for all that, and then on the cut, he
hops out.
This is one of the scenes where Robert's trainer had notes on lighting. He's like, can we just get the top
light? He goes, alright, okay, this is terrible. This is good lighting.
For you right here, top light. You look like Rocky II, man, where you all cut up and shredded.
"You more shredded than a julienne salad, man"
How funny is he in Tropic Thunder? Forget it.
He sent me a picture of him in the makeup from Tropic Thunder. I was like, you're kidding, right?
That's going to be breaking about the time we're coming out, and they're going to be boycotting our movie.
He says, maybe, but I think it's going to work out. Sure enough, there was no backlash.
The R-word [retard] that was in the story.
It might be the first time in Marvel
history that we allude to the fact that one of the lead characters may have had an evening with a tranny.
Because that was also improvised.
So this next little bit of business here,
and working on the suit, he just...
This is all... We're late in the game...
This whole interface where he interacts with the hologram was something we were just...
I was like, Robert, just move your hands
around. I'll put something in around you.
But just move the thing.
And we got contacted by the military saying, How did you know about this technology?
And they actually asked us for permission to use this stuff
as a demonstration of what their stuff does, because they can't do it yet.
This is a 60 mile an hour windstorm.
They were going to call it a weather day. I said, No, no, no.
Hand out goggles. This was even windier the day you were shooting.
And it has... It gives it that weird... Something feels like Star Wars about this.
I kind of get it.
If anybody wants to know what happens when three boulders fall on your head, that's what it looks like.
We did the research. This is a great piece of...
Just the negative space on the mask and him wearing the goggles. I thought it was really cool.
Those goggles I pulled off of our assistant visual effects supervisor. He ordered them from China.
Army surplus goggles. I said, Those. Give him a hand.
By the way, these were going to be several hundred thousand scenes where I'm just doing the Tony Stark tweaks with his machines and
all that. See that in the background? The gantry on the ceiling?
That's digital. And that was a big argument with the studio, because if you didn't show that there,
you couldn't have him being suited up later.
That's there for you guys. So you can enjoy the movie.
That wasn't there. These are the two dumbest robots in history. They didn't do anything.
Therefore, I made them my friends.
So this is the first time I was ever involved with visual effects to this scale. And I always thought about...
Nobody ever uses it for humor.
And it's very hard to get the timing just right on this stuff, because it takes so many months.
Everybody's expecting something heroic here.
Is there someone standing around with a fire extinguisher? Jon goes, get him over here. What was the guy's name?
Jeter? The SFX guy? Günther.
Günther! Do you have a fire extinguisher?
Yeah, that's right. He stuck it on there. None of that's in the script.
That's my soul.
Here's another one.
I always felt like the best scene in Spider-Man, or the best scenes, were him learning to use this, climb the wall,
and use the web shooter- the learning curve.
So instead of rushing through this stuff, I really wanted to have fun and explore it.
And that was, I think, an improvised line.
This set we called the "Night Clubbers, Part 1."
He's playing a little soliare there. A little...
like in Amadeus
there's jealousy.
That's public domain, so I saved another 50 grand for Marvel.
Ray's Pizza. Thought it was a nice touch. Those of you from New York...
He's flying in on his G5. He's bringing pizza from Ray's Pizza.
So there's a constant tug-of-war here.
Because Marvel always wants it sort of straightforward, and we always want to do something different
and interesting, and...
We're afraid we'll confuse people if you learn up front enough about things. I think we struck a nice balance.
Those sound effects, too, by the way, came out of when we were up at Skywalker Ranch doing it,
so a lot of that stuff is...
Ben Burtt...
Those Ben Burtt sounds.
So that's a feeling like WALL-E or R2-D2 or Star Wars. It's just coming from the same library of sounds.
What is so funny about being mean to inanimate objects?
And because we went in order, if I threw a joke around like that...
That's how the whole runner came about, of the
fire extinguisher hitting him.
So he would make up a line like that, and then there would be an opportunity to pay it off later.
The humor, the humor, the humor. Come on.
And the script was pretty straight ahead. There wasn't a lot of humor in the script.
There was some dialogue that was clever, like the stuff you do with Pepper, but the action stuff was very straight ahead.
I was right before last time, and I felt like we'd done a good half-day at that point.
So look at the Army of Darkness suiting up shots.
So this HUD was another big thing. How do you show him inside the suit? Because this is the one suit where you
can actually get inside. In Spider-Man, you've got to take the mask off. In Batman, you can't do that.
This is just awesome right here. It's all ILM.
So some of this is CGI. I think they ended up replacing most of it with CGI.
We filmed a real suit, and then they did the collapse work. And that's Tom Morello playing guitar.
So everything on this HUD, we know what it means.
There's a whole thought process behind all these little widgets and calibrations.
We have a couple very special guest appearances coming up here.
Let's see.
We've got the Favreau children.
There we go.
We really want to capture that feeling of when you look up. I'm kind of afraid of flying.
And that feeling you get when you come into LAX and you're looking down.
That sort of grid, the electrical grid. The way it twinkles. What it really feels like.
You get a sense of vertigo.
That ice still looks like shit to me.
That was in the last step we were working on.
It's so fun because you drive home from work and you come up with ideas.
Wouldn't it be cool if there was a house on Point Dume? If I could fly, I would go past
the ferris wheel.
So if Robert hadn't improvised the line about don't spray me with that thing, then we never would have done that after.
So it was a real partnership. And I'd say some of the best moments, I guess it happens in every movement, some
of the best moments, certainly in this one, came from unexpected things happening. And really
following the improviser's creed that I was brought up with of just saying "yes and."
And this also led to something. It sure does. It figures into act 3, and was never
part of the script. It wasn't part of the script. It was just a prop I had made
that I thought would be a nice way for them to bond. Which was that she would take this thing
that he said throw away and then she made a little romantic gesture with it.
And then... Why didn't you ask him to twist the ring right there? Because it was already close enough in the
foreground? Yeah.
To lead people to believe we really know what we're doing... down the road. I like that little...
It's complicated.
It's precise. Take to heart. Yes.
And I turn over this shoulder.
So this is another big argument.
Marvel was like, why is he drinking the green shit?
And I said, Robert, his whole character, he's got a whole thing he's doing. They said, well, why?
I said, I don't know. I'll ask him.
He felt very strongly about it. Because he was healing his body using these superfoods.
Right? Wasn't that basically it? Yes.
By the way, there's nothing quite as fun as having an Arc Reactor surgically glued to your sternum every morning.
Again, so great to get the idea from the car that he worked on with his dad.
Which is actually Jon's car.
Audi power!
Look at that. I could always work on commercials if this doesn't work out.
This is... This is the best use of Stan Lee in a movie ever.
Coming up.
There you go.
Jeff's first night.
And Gwyneth's first night. In the movie.
She was... Gwyneth was like, I really work best
before like... eight or nine.
I said cool. It's that kids' idea. Yeah, I get it.
Sure enough, it was like three in the morning when she had her first shot.
I added that "Gift of the Stark Foundation" [on the wall]. It adds a little touch there.
So she's supposed to look the most ravishing in the whole movie as she ever does.
She doesn't dye her hair. She has beautiful blonde hair. So this is all wigs.
This red hair.
And...
I don't know that we really got there with this wig.
But I do like this scene a lot.
I like writing dialogue for this kind of stuff. They did a good job improvising around it.
But she said that. Gwyneth said that, when we were rehearsing. See what I do is I write down
everything that people say what they rehearse.
And she should say something. She should say something like, I'm not wearing
deodorant. And I'll just write everything down. And it would be in the script.
And I knew she'd do a good job with the lines because she said them already.
I usually like to make the character fit the actor more than the actor fit the character.
And I knew Gwyneth, and this is actually not far from what she... She's more like this than in most of
the roles that I've seen her in. And so just to find something that you can really knock out of park.
And really show what's charming and interesting and quirky about her.
I don't think there was anything written here. This is just me feeding you guys lines until it takes, right?
Say this, say this.
Two cameras.
This is one of those scenes where everybody from the studio is like looking at you like you're crazy because it's 4 in the
morning and you're doing ten takes and you're running in and you're telling them to say something completely different from the last time.
We actually, they did really kiss.
And through playing film backwards here and stopping things and using another focus shot...
we were able to piece together an almost-kiss. Look at her right now.
Cut that out, why is that in there? What does it mean?
You have to follow this. These are Jon's jokes that are kind of so quick and subtle that happen right now
that they almost need to be reiterated.
Leslie Bibb. She was a real, she was a treat.
Starring in Midnight Meat Train [2008]. I don't know whose thumbs they are, but it looks like a murderer.
Good looping, by the way, Robert. Look at that. Unusable sound here.
He's very good at that. I'll tell him. Picture time.
That's what Robert would say to me in every country. Picture time.
Should we tell him here? Should we not tell him here? Should we not?
I don't know. You're so adamant about it. When you watch the movie, it doesn't matter.
But we fight back and forth over those things for months on end. You can't tell him he filed the injunction
yet because of the... Nobody. Nobody cares.
Speaking of something else Jon said: I want you to just shut up, stare at the screen, be a badass,
and tweak your arm until I tell you to stand up. I was like, alright, dude.
Whatever. Just tell me 10 minutes before we shoot, I'm gonna do a set.
Now that was actually the real scene that we shot for the next action sequence that was shot by the second unit.
Not this part. That little steel mill back there. And it was with the real suit.
And it looked like an episode of Power Rangers. So we went back and used a CG
suit and did a reshoot with the thing with the... the CG suit.
So this wasn't originally in... And that's not Robert.
But ILM... Whoever that guy is...
But this is really awesome stuff that ILM did. It's all CG.
When we cut money from the budget to get our green light, all the stuff where he was suiting up we
cut out of the movie. Because we just cut from him getting ready to go to him in the suit, flying.
Because it didn't affect the story. Then Transformers came out and made all this money.
I said, guys, are you crazy? People are... We're gonna make $300 million just because
people watched trucks turn into suits.
We cut out everything in the movie...
Sound barrier.
So they gave us a couple million bucks more but we had no shootout sequences in the final moments of the film.
This is all reshoots.
So here's the trick with a superhero movie.
You gotta make it so that everybody could root for the guy.
If you just had Iron Man flying into some place killing a bunch of terrorists with low-tech weapons, and being a high-tech American hero,
in every part of the world-
it's tough to get behind that
the same way you get behind Spider-Man saving a woman getting mugged in Central Park.
So we have this little mini-scene that's interesting. That little boy is Faran's son.
The guy who plays the other bad guy by the way. That's our little boy.
This guy.
So it looks like he's about to see his dad's reveal. I love this guy.
I love gunfighter stuff. A little Robocop here.
That's a stuntman from the valley.
He's an Italian guy.
So... this is also from Robocop, right?
Did I steal that from Robocop?
It's nice to know that the people you just saved have stomped somebody to death.
This is CG. CGI right here. All of this.
It's pretty amazing.
Looks real.
This is from the original test that The Orphanage [VFX studio] did for us.
That was four figures in the movie.
Now can somebody tell me why he doesn't use that against Jeff Bridges at the end? I don't know.
He's saying the missile system is disabled.
Whatever.
We shot this scene twice and we rewrote it for a thousand years.
I couldn't... We got it right though. I couldn't let go.
But it sucked before and now it's good.
So it actually came off. The re-shoots actually worked out really, really
well for the first time in history.
But the little interplay, the little interpersonal interplay between Robert and Terrence really made the scene keep the personality of the rest of the film.
And that was because Robert showed up for the re-shoots here and actually was off camera working with him and they improvised once again.
That was a nice touch there.
So this was one of the original stuff we used for Comic-Con.
Many of these are actual... actual plates where we had real airplanes doing this
so that the sky movement, even though we painted over all the planes, felt real.
It didn't feel like a big CG environment.
So these were all real plates with real lens flare and real scratches.
And of course mixed in are some CG.
The cell phone is also going to be the theme from the 60s part here.
We looked at Battlestar Galactica a lot. We really liked the camera work from that. How imperfect it was.
The long lens work.
Courtesy of Empire Strikes Back.
The A/V had audio video toasters- it looks like a television station if you really look at the equipment.
So we have real skydivers and stuff.
They didn't have a real chair strapped to them, but we did have real skydivers when we were taking the chair in.
I tried to do as much practical as I could for the plates. I was very, very reticent about it having
too much of a CG look.
We mix it up enough that I think that we really pulled it off where it's not glaring in your face, that something's fake.
So Robert had improvised a line about the training exercise, and then I said, Oh, let's
shoot a press conference where he says the training exercise. So, apparently, this is also part of the reshoot-
apparently Obadiah Stane lives in a prop rental house.
So if you don't have any money, just... See how he has his collar flipped up on his pajamas?
Listen to this dialogue, it's so wrong.
Another reshoot.
I don't know who came up with that, if it was Robert or me, but it just happened.
A laugh at the end of a scene or action sequence will save you the scrutiny that you would otherwise be subject to.
So basically all the stuff that was supposed to be plot wise, significant stuff, never really landed that hard.
So I just tried to make the movie as fun and funny as it could be.
So there's just enough of this stuff to make you believe it's a movie, I guess.
The parking lot at Buena Vista.
I remember I wasn't working that day and I drove by and I go, wow, here's the big scene.
Again, if you like the dialogue in any of these scenes, there's a four times as long version of every scene.
So that's an effect, a CG effect that a company called LOMA did for us, those veins.
And this effect with this cheap little prop and the cheap little lights in the ears, it was like...
And the acting, how do you act when you're paralyzed? What did Jeff do when you said, how
would you do it? Jeff said, how is he going to do the paralysis thing?
I said, you're an Academy Award nominated actor, show me. And he flipped on the floor and shook
around like an alligator. God bless him. I said, you're arguably one of the best
actors of our generation. And that looked terrible. So if you can't do it, how can
I ask these people to do it? And so it turned into them just being frozen.
And then it looked like hell. We'll get to that later. So finally, we added that little visual effect
that cost a couple grand that really sold the whole thing. It was amazing how sometimes it's that last
little whipped cream that sells the whole thing. More importantly, this is where Jon Favreau saved my career.
There was a cut of the scene where I flipped a table over while I'm getting emphatic.
And on the playback, he told me I look not exactly like Prince.
It wasn't even a table, it was a dentist tray with instruments on it. There it is.
Next to the iron lung, or whatever else was in the prop house.
You don't understand, it looks so like decisive.
This is literally stuff that was used for like, you know, 1950s
episodes of The Hulk or something.
This is one of those scenes where we were up all night with people on set writing, wasn't it?
I can't believe we're doing another one of these.
They're good actors because... I don't know what's going on.
There's nothing except the next mission!
I mean, who do you sell that garbage to?
But you gotta have it. If you don't have it though, the movie doesn't work.
This is some nice sets, that [J. Michael] Riva built for us.
And I'm saying, wait a minute. What is this, War Games? She's going to go into this thing.
And she's going to do this with the fob. And he's going to come in and go... We're going to get slammed [by critics]!
They're going to kill us. He [Jon] is like it's gonna be fine-
Just because you're not in the scene doesn't mean it won't turn out.
So we tried to create a whole interface, desktop for Stark, like he had his own thing. I mean, just hours of meetings.
You really have to be obsessive to be a director.
Because you spend 90% of your time picking fly shit out of pepper.
They're like, what colors? How many folders should there be?
They ask you and you have to tell them because you're the director.
See, how it works? You just type in "translate."
It's the same actor who reads the line.
Oh, you found my Translite.
I hate Translites. This one was actually pretty good.
Thank you.
Somebody enjoyed that.
I always enjoy that.
They're in Tony's office and... there we go, cover it up with the Financial Times. He says, I like the puzzle.
The Financial Times doesn't have a puzzle.
For those of you who direct movies:
You're in a lot of meetings and people talk about how much box office people make or who's the cost or this or that
or who's hot. Always, always go with the best actor.
Because... it will save your ass.
But you kind of know what you're doing and you're kind of telling them what the scene's about and you kind of think you
know what's happening.
There's something that happens when good actors get together and they bring an authenticity to the
subtext of the scene.
That... it's a little bit of a shell game. And they...
they just...
bring significance to things that don't have any significance and bring gravity to things that don't
justify it. And...
it just classes everything up a lot. And we still have the same problems with this film that we had before...
Why did you make her look at the fob in her hand even though we already see that she's got it?
Then this was... When do we cut to this? I'm not standing for this stuff next time,
I'll tell you that much.
All the freedom in the world won't stand.
It's actually funny. I like this with Clark [Gregg]. This feels...
[Comparing hero archetypes] Eliot Ness from Untouchables... the accountant [Oscar Wallace]...
Thanks, David [Hayter, writer]. Peter Billingsley here [Ralphie, A Christmas Story].
Did you just pay for one day's work?
Now I kind of know why I didn't have to do a commentary.
Because we didn't really have much to say, do we? About this.
Damn straight you're not.
All right. This was the biggest trust exercise of my life.
Because remember he was going to bring a box of pizza from Chicago? Yeah, yeah.
I said I should have a gun under the table, and instead he said, no, just sit there frozen.
While Jeff reads 39 pages of commentary.
But those veins [VFX] helped. The veins did everything.
And then the other thing that he pulls out the heart thing with... It's good.
It's like a little machined aluminum prop that we added claws to in post-production.
Just notice the great Jeff Bridges technique of taking his time.
Sometimes about 12 seconds between each word.
Look at that.
That's pretty cool.
See, in independent films, you don't have all this stuff to save you.
All the little funny special effects and things.
I like how Matty lit it with the light from that and it glints in his eyes.
I like that line about the atomic bomb.
We'll be here for hours, too.
See there's going to be a SHIELD logo right there... there ya go. We snuck that in.
We added that in post-production.
And of course, another Audi.
Because after all, how would they get around if not for Audis?
This one's like hollowed out. And here, this is another discovery.
So of course that's since we shot in order.
There's a Stark 5, as opposed to a Mach 5.
So as we were writing, as we were going along, we said, where's he going to get the heart if he gets the heart
to the suit? And it was like, of course, the one that Pepper gave him.
I always like the notion of people using things from display cases. You know, like, oh yeah, we figured out
how he gets it.
His little friend.
Now he was actually, he actually starred in the commercial about the assembly line robot.
Remember that for the Super Bowl [2007]?
There's an assembly line robot that gets fired and wants to kill itself.
Stan Winston built that, and they said,
we'll have it for the background, and the puppeteers were having fun with it.
And I told Robert, don't worry, we're going to have high-tech stuff in the shop,
because you're Tony Stark, and it showed up, and it was these things.
And that's why he ridiculed them the whole
movie, because he said, this is not what Tony Stark would have.
No, they were the dumbest robots ever invented.
Where's Pepper? That was the one line that he refused to say in the whole movie.
It's Tony, where's Pepper? Kent Brody: we must find Obadiah. I was like, I won't do it.
I refused to say, where's Pepper?
Jeremy Latcham, the co-producer, would always come up, because he worked for Marvel,
and he'd be like, what we really need you to say in this scene is, where's Pepper?
And he would just ride him.
Here, remember, sector 16, down here is section 16.
It doesn't seem to matter.
There it is, section 16. Here's my little cinematic thing there. There's a pull-back.
I like this- more my speed.
So that was like the joke that they made.
Look how he just folds his arms.
But that's the type of stuff they kept trying to make me cut out. And I'd slip a little bit back in.
They'd make me cut it out. It makes you weak and unlikable. No, it makes her human and cool.
You're in the real suit for this. This is Robert in the real suit.
Keep the skies clear.
So that wasn't in the script either, but we just saw it hanging there. And we said, wouldn't it be funny if...
Let's do the entire sequel on that moment.
We're like, should he be trying to put the helmet on? It can't fit.
So we just had the "next time, baby."
What did they say this is? The Ridley Scott homage? Alien kind of.
Yeah, that was a shot from Alien.
Most of the shots I steal I remember. I remember consciously stealing them.
This one was subconscious. But I think this is a shot from Alien coming up, though not done as well.
So now you need that shot to show that he didn't die.
That was a big argument. Oh, geez.
Here's the shot of him jumping over the rail.
Yes.
And the world is safe once again.
This one.
The chain spread.
Heavily storyboarded.
That was Gwen running on a broken leg. She didn't know she had a broken leg.
She said my leg's hurting a little bit.
Why the hell is there a tank with like a label on it? Like they sell tanks.
With a mileage sticker on it.
This one has airbags.
That's pretty cool.
Roxxon, for you Marvel fans, there's a couple Roxxon logos
on the trucks.
This dialogue when superheroes are fighting is the hardest thing you've ever heard. Up to the looping stage.
It's so hard to make it sound bad.
I like that.
There's a Roxxon logo.
So originally, he was supposed to be... Rhodey was going to come up in the R8 and ram into him and knock
him into the hydrogen bus, and the bus was going to blow up. I thought that was funny.
He was going to just fall gingerly into the hydrogen bus and it was going to blow up
like the Hindenburg. And that's where that plate was from. So, the car came up and would hit
him, bang him into it, and instead we used that explosion for this. But that was what was going to happen
when he fell gingerly into the hydrogen bus.
So, Audi was not very happy when they heard what we did.
This is all new. So, the last action sequence wasn't seen to have enough action when we cut that out.
And so, it was like three weeks left to create a new action sequence in the end.
And so, all of this stuff with the flying of all re-purposed plates and CGI that was done by ILM.
And then we shot this in the reshoot. It was more than three weeks, but it was not enough time.
So, we used a training exercise bit again, to tie it together.
And we tried to call back to the ice thing, but there was something in the setup that wasn't as strong as it
should have been.
We're gonna have a hell of an Act 3 next time, I promise.
Cut.
I'm still standing here.
That's the one.
That was a Robert mask on a stunt double.
A rubber Robert mask...
That's pretty cool.
All the little pieces moving around in there.
It was actually like a little, what we call the teapot, which was a...
It was a...
It was a piece that was on a dolly that they would push and he could move back and forth to emulate the movement
of the suit and we were going to build the suit around him, which we did.
We were going to start to integrate him more into the actual movement of the suit, and he felt pasted on.
When we looked at the stuff of Doc Ock, it was like he was floating in front of a green screen and we
wanted to have more parallax and more perspective shift and so we designed a whole rig for him.
That's all miniatures.
That whole inside the silo was miniature. I'm a big fan of miniatures- that special effects.
This is a completely practical effect coming up.
Right there.
Real missile, real arms, real actor, real explosion. Everything else was doctored in some way.
Why didn't Pepper die?? Well, there's the answer...
Get it...?
Weird Science!
He was supposed to land, and there were more hanging there with dead suits for another five days of dialogue.
And we left it out, after we paid for the CG. That explosion brought helicopters and the police force.
He said we were going to have an explosion at 10, but we thought something went wrong.
We fried $180,000 worth of lights, our second unit did. We went on an insurance claim.
Now, once again, I like the dialogue. Gotta have good actors. But that's just me.
So we got in a lot of trouble for that [newspaper] picture up there
because when we were filming on the highway, some people from a website
snuck in and filmed us filming, and put that on their website. Those were the first pictures that came out.
I thought it would be really fun to put the picture from the picture they took from us as the picture in the movie.
It was really cool, and then they sued Marvel for $5 million.
So I don't know where it settled, but that's what you get for trying to be cool.
That's the cover story from the comic books, by the way. Iron Man was his bodyguard.
So we pay homage to it. This is how we work SHIELD in.
I didn't think you guys would believe that.
So this was two cameras completely improvised. We got three versions of this scene that I loved.
Getting a lot of truth in Robert doing his thing.
I'm going to look right in the pipe for this right here.
I am Iron Man.
So...
But that seemed like a really good idea to tell everyone, I am Iron Man.
Until...
Until we set out to make the next one and we're like, wow, everybody knows he's Iron Man.
I don't know what the heck he does. He can either wake up from a dream,
or we gotta live with it.
And it's actually cool because it makes it different from all the superhero movies now.
I love, by the way, these low-tech, like, line vector graphics.
Of course, Marvel was saying, hey, why don't we have... Oh, there's the Ten Rings thing.
There's a little War Machine- a little teaser for the next movie.
But I love the...
I love the line vector, low-tech, shuddering,
you know, bad-com looking credit sequence here.
And of course, Marvel wanted 3D CGI, like Spider-Man...
But I just... I just got this. And that's the SHIELD logo.
So, ya know Jonny... We have a bonus scene. What's he talking?
We got six minutes, guys. If you have to pee, go run out and come back.
So, I had the Sam Jackson scene here. And then, up in ILM... not ILM, up in Skywalker...
Edgar Wright, the director, came out.
He was like the first person to see this in the Stag Theater at Skywalker.
Skywalker, by the way, just to be able to mix a movie at Skywalker in the Kurosawa mixing stage was phenomenal.
Because Lucas built, you know, basically a whole facility for him. And he rents it out to other people
to make it a business. But it's like what you would do if you had all the money in the world,
were a complete film geek, and wanted to collect every authentic film poster there was, and build everything
as though Frank Lloyd Wright had built it, in the most beautiful part of the world you could buy real estate in- this part of
Marin County, just thousands of acres.
But anyway, Edgar Wright was up there visiting.
And I showed him this film. He says, I love it! I love it!
I love it! It's great! Really?
Oh, it's great! He says, the one thing you gotta do, he says, you can't have that bonus scene
right there.
Put it at the end of the credits. I said, really? He says, yeah.
Don't just give it to them. Put it all the way at the end. Let people miss it.
I said, really? He says, yes.
So, of course, then Marvel, when they saw that I switched it to the end, was like, why the hell did you do that?
And then the word got out that there was a scene at the end. And then people came back to see the
movie just to see the 30 second scene.
And I think the fact that they have such a long credit sequence here that people
would sit through, it was responsible for $10 million at the box office.
So then Jon says, so hey, listen, we're just going to shoot some of these things for like, you know, a little bomb shoot.
They'll probably ask you to do one for the Hulk, whatever. So, you're just going to come into your
house but someone's broke in. And I said, god damn it. After everything he's been through, wouldn't he have upped
his security? So I'm thinking again, like I say, why can he just walk into his house and so you
would be like, well, he's from SHIELD. And I said, god damn it.
It doesn't make any sense.
He goes, well, Sam Jackson's gonna do it.
So here he is.
So Sam Jackson's the guy that in The Ultimate Avengers, for you guys who know comic books,
they made look like Sam Jackson. I said, wouldn't that be cool for the fans?
This is a Marvel movie. First time Marvel Studios is making its own movies.
Let's put as many little Easter eggs for the fans in there as we can. So we asked Sam, do you want to
do it? He said, sure. He came down, we kept it top secret.
We shot on a Saturday. Skeleton crew, nobody. It literally got out the next day.
So we struck all of our screening prints and even the premiere did not have the scene.
And everybody was up in arms because: You said it was in. It wasn't in. I knew it was in.
What did they do? What did they do? And then when it finally went to the
real theaters, we put the print back in with it on. And I think that the fans appreciated the
cat and mouse game we played. And so this went very well. And then for The Hulk, they said, hey,
why don't you do one for after the credits too?
And Robert says, should I do it? I said, why not? It's after the credits, whatever.
He goes and does it. And at the last minute, they decide instead of having it at the end of the credits, they ended
the movie with it.
It became the big ending of the movie.
Then Robert was going to walk in because... They were hoping I'd like to come and
see that they had made that change at the premiere.
And I was otherwise engaged. It was all part of the Marvel universe, and it was a marvelous universe.
But now if we do a sequel, we're trying to figure out what he's... In that movie, he goes up to the
bad guy and says, we're forming a team.
And clearly at the end of this movie, he's not forming a team of anything.
So where're we putting it in the timeline? How does he justify? Does he wake up from a dream?
That's always my part. He can wake up from a dream! Oh, okay.
It was a training exercise.
We pull back and it's a movie set in the movie. Like in Get Shorty.
See, we don't think about this stuff while we're doing it. That's what nobody knows.
You're just trying to bail water out of the boat.
You know? You get your fingers in all the holes in the dam.
And then you're so happy, and you're exhausted after you run the marathon.
And then you pick yourself up, and then
you realize you're only... You've got to do it again. By the way, for their code of loving
tolerance, I think we should give a hand to Joya Favreau and Susan Downey. Thank you.
Who stuck by our sides through thick and thin.
My wife, Joya, has left. She's not here anymore. Not the marriage, just the screening.
She's heard me talk enough. It got to the point where Susan would just come in and hand me the phone...
I'd go, who is this? Your girlfriend's on the phone.
I don't think that was me.
What about Captain America?
Oh yeah, I should have said that.
So there's a shield, a Captain America shield in the background of when he says, this
isn't the worst thing you caught me doing, that scene.
There's a shield in there with the Captain America logo on it, on his workbench. That was put in by a ILM guy.
And they showed it to us as a joke in the screening sessions. They were like, leave it in, man.
They love that kind of thing. Leave it in. And everybody picked it out.
Of course, it's like the person hanging themselves in Wizard of Oz now- it is really there?
So here comes scene that everybody waits 15 minutes to see.
As the run was coming up, more and more people would stay in the theater. In the beginning, it would just be like
10. By the end, it would be the whole house.
Here it is.